{"tossups": [{"question": "In this body of water, the Buduma people inhabit the Bogomerom Archipelago. During the Sayfuwa dynasty, a highway between Tripoli and this lake traded horses for slaves from the Bornu Empire. The Transqua project tried to divert the Ubangi River into this lake, whose shrinkage was declared an ecological disaster by the FAO. Niger, Nigeria, and Cameroon share, for the point, what shallow lake in the African Sahel also shared by a namesake country with a capital at N\u2019Djamena?", "answer": "Lake<b> Chad</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "This civilization\u2019s kukkutarma site may have bred chickens for religious purposes, rather than food. The \u201cpriest-king\u201d statue and Pashupati seal were artifacts from this civilization, which also constructed the earliest known public water tank. This civilization\u2019s Citadel Mound became the site of the Great Bath. Harappa and \u201cthe mound of the dead,\u201d Mohenjo-daro, were sites in, for the point, what Bronze Age-era civilization that thrived in Pakistan near a namesake river?", "answer": "<b> Indus</b> Valley Civilization (accept<b> IVC</b>; accept<b> Harappa</b>n Civilization before it is read)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "In his diary, an attendee of this event said he wouldn\u2019t stay all summer \u201cjust to listen to speeches. I\u2019ll go home to the Senate for that.\u201d This meeting concluded that a country\u2019s eastern border would shift westwards to the Oder-Neisse line. A declaration named for this meeting declared that if Japan did not surrender, it faced \u201cprompt and utter destruction.\u201d This conference was the first meeting to feature Prime Minister Clement Attlee and President Harry Truman. For the point, name this 1945 conference held by the \u201cBig Three\u201d Allied powers in occupied Germany.", "answer": "<b> Potsdam</b> Conference", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "A document outlining this group\u2019s ideology was studied by Sylvain Besson in the book<em> The Conquest</em> <em>of the West</em>. This group, whose terrorist wing is known as the \u201csecret apparatus,\u201d was founded by Hassan al-Banna in Ismailia in 1928. Members of the Free Officers Movement cracked down on this movement after accusing them of attempting to assassinate Nasser, and they came to power after a 2011 revolution after Mohamed Morsi was elected. Mohamed Morsi led the Freedom and Justice Party, a political party linked with, for the point, what Islamist group in Egypt?", "answer": "<b> Muslim Brotherhood</b> (accept<b> Society of the Muslim Brothers</b>; accept<b> al-Ikhwan al-Muslimun</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "A war named after this number of days was ended by the Brioni Accords; that first of the Yugoslav Wars was the Slovenian War of Independence. Dutch King William I launched a campaign named after this number of days that failed to stop the Belgian Revolution of 1830. American journalist John Reed wrote [this number of]<em> Days That Shook the World</em>, which documented Russia\u2019s October Revolution. For the point, the French Revolutionary calendar dictated that how many days should be the new version of a week, called a decade?", "answer": "<b> 10</b> days", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A C minor piece of this type was dedicated to the composer\u2019s psychiatrist Nikolai Dahl, who helped cure him of depression. Before conducting a piece of this type by Brahms, Leonard Bernstein sparked controversy when he disavowed the \u201cremarkably broad tempi\u201d of performer Glenn Gould. Sergei Prokofiev wrote one of these works for Paul Wittgenstein, who lost his right hand in World War I. For the point, name this type of musical work for orchestra and a keyboard soloist.", "answer": "<b> piano concerto</b>s [prompt on partial answers, like \u201cconcerto\u201d or \u201cpiano music\u201d]", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {}, {}, {"question": "This organization fired Ruth Bates Harris after she delivered a report to James Fletcher stating that its equal opportunity program was \u201ca total failure.\u201d Margaret Hamilton was pictured next to a massive pile of binders that she and her team wrote for this organization. Mary Jackson, Katherine Johnson, and Dorothy Vaughan worked as \u201ccomputers\u201d for this organization, as recounted in the book<em> Hidden</em> <em>Figures</em>. For the point, name this US governmental agency that, in 1983, helped Sally Ride become the first American woman in space.", "answer": "<b> NASA</b> (accept<b> National Aeronautics and Space Administration</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "After being captured on this body of water, the Edmunson sisters had their freedom purchased by Henry Ward Beecher\u2019s church; over 70 other slaves were captured during that escape attempt, the 1848 Pearl Incident. Bans on dredging this body of water were ignored by \u201cpirates\u201d during the Oyster Wars. This body of water\u2019s namesake flotilla carried the troops that burned Washington during the War of 1812. The Potomac River empties into, for the point, what bay of the Atlantic Ocean that separates the Delmarva Peninsula from Virginia?", "answer": "<b> Chesapeake</b> Bay (prompt on Potomac River before \u201cOyster\u201d is read)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This country relocated farmers to communal agricultural settlements in Operation Vijiji. In what is now this country, Hamad Bin Thuwaini was killed in 1896, sparking a 38-minute war with England. This country\u2019s first president founded the Chama Cha Mapinduzi party and created a policy of \u201cvillagization\u201dbased on the concept of ujamaa; that man outlined his socialist principles in the Arusha Declaration. For the point, name this African country that was first ruled by Julius Nyerere and which formed from the union of Tangyanika and Zanzibar.", "answer": "United Republic of<b> Tanzania</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "This leader founded the League of Princes to oppose the swap of Bavaria for the Netherlands. This leader secured a British alliance in the Westminster Convention during the Diplomatic Revolution. After defeats at Kunersdorf and Kolin, this man was saved by the death of Empress Elizabeth in the \u201cMiracle of the House of Brandenburg.\u201d This ruler conspired with Russia and Austria in the First Partition of Poland, but fought them in the War of the Austrian Succession. For the point, name this enlightened despot of Prussia.", "answer": "<b> Frederick the Great</b> (accept<b> Frederick II</b> of Prussia; prompt on Frederick)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "Arthur St. Clair was removed as governor of this territory after saying that its people had no more an obligation to listen to Congress than they did to the first consul of France. As part of Jay\u2019s Treaty, British soldiers withdrew from forts in this territory. The 1787 ordinance that established this territory specifically banned slavery within it, leading the Ohio River to serve as the dividing line between free and slave states. For the point, name this massive tract of land that included what became Illinois, Indiana, and Ohio.", "answer": "<b> Northwest Territory</b> (accept the<b> Old Northwest</b>; accept<b> Territory Northwest</b> of the River Ohio)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "During this period, the Jesuit priests Francisco Jalics and Orlando Yorio were kidnapped. The Montoneros were a guerrilla group during this period, many of whose leaders were pardoned by president Carlos Menem but retried under Nestor Kirchner. The Mothers of the Plaza de Mayo mourned children who disappeared during this campaign, which began after a military junta installed Jorge Rafael Videla and overthrew Isabel Peron. For the point, name this 1976-1983 period in which leftists were suppressed in Argentina.", "answer": "<b> Dirty War</b> (or<b> Guerra Sucia</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This meeting reaffirmed the agreements laid out in the Council of Chaumont. The Grand Duchy of Posen was created as a compromise in this meeting in order to block Russia\u2019s claim to all of the Duchy of Warsaw. Under this meeting\u2019s Final Act, kings were restored to their pre-war thrones. The Concert of Europe was borne from this meeting, which was chaired by Klemens von Metternich. For the point, name this meeting in Austria that aimed to decide the fate of post-Napoleonic Europe.", "answer": "<b> Congress of Vienna</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "With his brothers Heman and Zimri, this man created the land-speculating Onion River Company. This man led a group that included Seth Warner, whose men captured Fort Crown Point in May 1775 as part of a mission that ended with Henry Knox dragging artillery across Massachusetts. After the war, this man became a leading advocate for Vermont\u2019s statehood. Fort Ticonderoga was captured by men under, for the point, what Founding Father who led the Green Mountain Boys?", "answer": "Ethan<b> Allen</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A photograph taken during this war depicting Frederick Borrell Garcia being shot at the Battle of Cerro Muriano was claimed to be staged because there was no negative in the \u201cMexican Suitcase.\u201d Robert Capa\u2019s<em> Falling Soldier</em> was photographed during this war, which also inspired a painting that depicts a flower growing out of a broken sword. The Condor Legion\u2019s bombing of a town inspired Pablo Picasso to paint<em> Guernica</em> during, for the point, what war that led to the rise of Francisco Franco?", "answer": "<b> Spanish Civil</b> War", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "This ruler pretended to abdicate for a year in favor of Simeon Bekbulatovich as part of a political ploy to seize the assets of his country\u2019s monasteries. After accusing Archbishop Pimen of treason, this ruler carried out the massacre of Novgorod with the help of the oprichniki. The death of this ruler\u2019s son Feodor I led to the end of the Rurikid Dynasty and sparked the Time of Troubles. For the point, name this first tsar of Russia whose nickname is more accurately translated as formidable.", "answer": "<b> Ivan IV</b> (accept<b> Ivan the Terrible</b>; accept<b> Ivan Grozny</b>; prompt on \u201cIvan\u201d)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Andrew Johnson, Harry Truman, and this man are the only Presidents to have at least 10 vetoes overridden by Congress. During this man\u2019s presidency, a soldier at Fort Dix mysteriously died after a swine flu epidemic. This man, who rejected Abraham Beame\u2019s request for a federal bailout, promoted the \u201cWIN\u201d program, which promised to \u201cWhip Inflation Now.\u201d Upon taking office, he proclaimed \u201cour long national nightmare is over\u201d and controversially pardoned his predecessor. For the point, name this president who succeeded Richard Nixon.", "answer": "Gerald Rudolph<b> Ford</b> Jr. (or Leslie Lynch<b> King</b> Jr.)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This city became famous for its hetairai at the extravagant Temple of Aphrodite, leading Horace to write that \u201cnot everyone is able to go to [this city.]\u201d Periander was responsible for creating the coinage of this city. After Lucius Mummius burnt this city to the ground, a namesake alloy was discovered from this city\u2019s melting bronze. This city names a style of column featuring curving scrolls that was developed after the Ionic and Doric orders. The Isthmian Games were held in, for the point, what ancient Greek city-state?", "answer": "<b> Corinth</b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "2 million purchase price was agreed to by this Secretary of State for a land deal decried as his \u201cFolly.\u201d For the point, name this politician who secured the purchase of Alaska.", "answer": "William<b> Seward</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "An object named for this material descended from the sky to land on Osei Tutu\u2019s lap; that object, the royal throne of the Ashanti, is a stool made from this material. Cairo took twelve years to recover from inflation caused by the immense spending of this resource during Mansa Musa\u2019s pilgrimage to Mecca. The trading of this resource and salt across the Sahara contributed greatly to the wealth of the Mali Empire. For the point, name this precious metal.", "answer": "<b> gold</b> (accept<b> gold</b>en stool) <b>Extra Question</b> Only read if moderator botches a question.", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "An uprising in this kingdom was led by generals including Prokop the Shaven and John the One-Eyed. This kingdom, which converted to Christianity under the Premyslid Dynasty, was defeated at the Battle of White Mountain. Rebels in this kingdom were inspired by the teachings of Jan Hus. Two Austrian agents were tossed out a window in this kingdom in an event that began the Thirty Years\u2019 War. For the point, name this kingdom in the modern-day Czech Republic.", "answer": "<b> Bohemia</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}], "bonuses": []}